so
[Music]
all right
hello and welcome everyone
it is active livestream number 47.1
on august 10th
and we're continuing our explorations
into the paper dyad inactive dynamic
social cognition and active inference
of hippalito and venice
and active inference and abduction by
pietarennen and benny
welcome to the act imp institute we're a
participatory lab and institute that is
communicating learning and practicing
applied active inference links are on
the slide
this is recorded in an archive live
stream so please provide us with
feedback so we can improve our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome
and we'll be following video etiquette
for live streams
head over to
activeinference.org to learn more about
other projects at the institute and how
to participate and join learning groups
today in
stream 47.1
we're continuing to learn and discuss
this pair of papers mentioned earlier
and on the previous video
and
we're going to open with some
introductions and then probably just
jump in wherever
anyone has a new
question they'd like to ask maybe ending
the introductions with blue so that you
can
bring um a new vector into the
conversation
so
i'm daniel i'm a researcher in
california
and i'm looking forward to
taking a 0.1
lens a little bit to the paper
which had
an extended
dot 0 as there was so much to learn
on a few of these angles and so much to
kind of think about
that um
[Music]
what is the difference between
being in the bathtub and then in the
middle
of
the paper pair
versus for example coming into it to
contextualize it or trying to leave it
to apply it something in between even
there
i'll pass it to uh dean
thanks i'm dean i'm here in calgary um
i don't know if uh i don't know what the
dot one means because we've never done a
dot one where we've tried to pull two
things
put them proximal and see what happens
because sometimes that's
fire and water and just get a lot of
steam and sometimes it's uh nitro and
glycerin and the whole thing blows up on
you so i'm kind of looking forward to
that that's kind of the
risky part that i think is kind of
exciting i'll pass it over to stephen
hello thanks dean yes stephen here i'm
in toronto um
i'm really curious around
what this infusion of two different
approaches
to active influence can yield so
what's behind it all you know what's
behind
an approach of an activism that brings
in instrumentalism
or an approach that's more
mathematically focused bringing in
realism so i'm curious and hopefully
it's going to be useful and practical
i'm going to pass it over to
blue
hi i'm blue i'm in new mexico
i really um enjoyed reading so i've read
the i think we did the um hippolyto
paper before on another live stream um
and so i've read that one before but i
really enjoyed reading this
abduction and active in french paper i
do not have
like a strong philosophy background so i
kind of come at this like with a what is
this what is that like i have to go
search wikipedia 100 million times to
kind of get more information um about
from a philosophical um aspect and so
one of the key things like where i was
having a hard time like locking in
on this abduction paper active inference
and abduction
is um
why
do first in blankets
like like uh they presented the authors
presented it as if the first and
blankets like necessitate a realist
perspective so so is that true and if so
why is that
all right
thanks everyone
so two
threads blue in what i
heard and i think two areas for us to
kind of
get on the slide and and see at the same
time
so one was like different approaches
that can be taken both by an individual
like different backgrounds in
different fields or disciplines
and then kind of going beyond one
person's just learning trajectory
and thinking what are the
conceptual approaches that we can take
to in this case active inference
but this might be
studying active inference and applying
active inference kind of both ways might
come into play
and then the question of the first and
blankets
something like what aspects of what
enable
a situational realist
or a
instrumentalist
why are people taking the stances
they're taking
[Music]
on a given situation
sometimes even like
mixed across different contexts for the
same system they might use one or
another or something like that stephen
and this brings action back into the
equation i sense that action is is quite
important because
the idea of instrumentalism is in a way
is there's a use of
certain instruments um and that's that's
the best way
to think of what's happening with the
blankets actually i think it's really
cool that you brought the blankets up
because uh
that that question of
uh comes you know in an active way it's
like the the temptation is to make
everything realist and then it's like
okay we've got a blanket so it's kind of
like well
maybe we should make sure we keep the
blanket question in an instrumental way
to avoid all those traps and then on the
other side it's like
on the math side it's like well
these
potentially fundamental
dynamics
well as they're being acted in some way
they must have some relation to reality
in some way
so it's sort of almost the mirror
it's not the mirror but it's something
that's sitting on the other side
in an interesting way i don't know what
dean thinks from that point but um
[Music]
i i i
was going to mention that i
i think if we are taking two papers and
actually
doing
a bit of a what happens when they get
entangled thing we're looking at what
happens when something is actively
inferred as a process as opposed to
active inference as a subject matter or
topic
and so when we do that we're essentially
asking
what the big questions on one of the
next slide here is
so is active inference both as process
as actively inferring and of process
something falls out of that and we
we asked it in the in the using the
metaphor of being both a gripper
right something as processing and a
process being gripped and so um
yeah i think if we if we
if we actually look at it as what's
what's going on not just from the
doing sense but from the
observing sense or participatory sense
um
i think it leaves us with no choice but
to
say that there's got to be some
going back and forth between both but
that's just my
take
so let me let me read this quote from
the paper um specifically going back to
to the blanket the one that that set off
my my my question bell that's like
unanswered
um it says
um okay according to recent
interpretations of the fep the dynamical
interaction of living systems and the
external world under active inference
can be interpreted semantically this is
a ramstead 2020 citation by assuming
that sensory states are meaningful
representations of the reality
this is especially the case if we assume
that the development of markov blankets
by fristen
unlike their original characterization
and works of judea pearl on
probabilistic causal networks admit a
realist interpretation of the
relationship between the organism and
the environment
so it says while the role of the
concepts of markov blankets and pearl
blankets in many treatments of the free
energy principle is an instrumentalist
one whereas in pierce's even stronger
terms concede to a nominalist
interpretation of their meaning first in
blankets are realist not only in the
non-instrumentalist sense but also in
the sense of being non-nominalist
entities the modal terms of references
to real possibilities such as what is
conceivable or produced by imagination
or anticipatorially related to the
future states of affairs are used in
making sense of the key aspects of the
theory
um
and and so in my recollection the first
in blanket like i didn't have that
linked to
realism necessarily per se
so
daniel like maybe ken do you have any
more clarification like is that like a
realist a first time blanket is a
realist interpretation of the pearl
blanket or or am i just forgetting that
when i read that part
i didn't know what nominalism was
so according to the summary
the view that universals and abstract
objects do not actually exist other than
being merely
names or labels
one version denies the existence of
universals
the other the abstract so it's an
anti-generalist position so let's see
where that was used with the first and
blanket
because this is the um
[Music]
crux
of the discussion like one of the
frontiers of contact
other than just saying well an activism
and dynamical systems theory work like
this coarsely or this broad area math
and chemistry work together like this
this is starting to get into the real
contact points of
turf
semantically that are being
vied over people have different
perspectives on
how to interpret
base graphs in different contexts
and so then the markov blanket
it's like it still might even be too
coarse grained
for that whole turf to be
controlled by one view or another
so then
let's look at
how the abduction paper
and anything else that you
see
where would it be more justified just in
your sense
um
[Music]
what and then we'll unpack this because
i think this was just copied in to
discuss today
since it's obviously a clear area where
both papers are talking about their view
on the markup blanket which might make
it clearer
to see how multiple views on
blankets and graphs
come into play
but let's unpack both of their
perspectives
seeing the nominalist um
interpretation and as as you're
unpacking that like it's something i
didn't have to look up because it's a
very um prominent theme in buddhism
right like that um you know
it's like the absence of any kind of
inherent existence like that existence
is nominal
and so it's interesting that in this um
abduction paper
that
they take this this um
you know construction by pierce of
nominalism but but also like more than
once in that paper they
point to an objective reality uh which
is like if if things are interp
interpreted if all stuff is nominally
interpreted
then
um
what is this objective reality other
than like linguistics or semantics or
perhaps semiotics
um yeah so
even
that's a very good point um because it
also ties back you mentioned about um
when we're talking there about the
relationship almost being the reality i
sensed that they were kind of saying if
there's a relationship
those relational
dynamics or they didn't use the word
dynamics therefore
have
some
can be called real you know
which i think is a fair assertion in
some senses
although
you know again
there could be an over extension because
there's a question about how much you go
up into transcendental
and how much you go down
into
the kind of more morphology and
the whole morphogenesis and there's
actually a really good there's a
hector lazar he's actually it does a lot
of work with theater of the oppressed
and worked with
you know people have been tortured and
stuff like that and he talks about
um the medicine is in the wounds the
medicine is in the wounds when people
get you know
trauma etc and one of the things that's
interesting there is that
we may be in a culture there's times
when we might try to explain things or
and do transcendental work
to to transcend a situation
or avoid us and we may actually avoid a
situation but sometimes when you go into
the wound
what you might find is is literally a
bloody mess
so
that may not be real in the normal sense
do you know
let's just add to that a little bit i
think it's interesting that most
representations of markov blankets show
the markov blanket
in between
two
distinct
um
sets of properties and that's always
represented on the horizontal
and i think what's interesting here is
that if if you
exactly if you find yourself
in a in a debate situation
of two top-down perspectives one that
says
it must be from the top down and active
or it must be from the top down some
some
series of
some series or set of different logics
applied depending upon your familiarity
with what it is that you're observing
that can lead to that whole question of
well
hierarchy and then what entails the
other so for me
um it's pretty it's pretty
easy to understand why
people who take
the exclusive position of
instrumentalism
as entailing
something like logic
or the other hierarchical
relationship of
the logic being the real thing
and then
the actions to follow or that's the
thing that's being entailed
i think what the diagrams a lot of the
pictures tell us is that there's a
lateral aspect to this as well
and so if we're going to
look at that lateral
less
which which is enveloping the other
top-down view because
both of the views in both of these
papers
the bias or the
the position that the authors take is
one of top down
what what rules
under this set of conditions or
circumstances
placing those two things side by each
strips away some of the questions around
relativity
and now introduces the idea of around
relationship not a relationship in terms
of power over
but relationship in terms of
what needs to be present in order for
somebody to be able to actually
make
fewer prediction errors
so
the markup blanket i think
can be
turned i mean right now most of it is is
perceived as being some sort of a
vertical partition between
lateral
elements i mean it can be flipped and
we've talked often in lots of papers
about what's the hierarchical structure
what's the bottom up what's the top down
but i think both of these papers
admittedly say
we are taking a top-down view of this
and therefore they are constraining
themselves to
more
emphasis on the relativity aspect of
what is going on in it in an actively
inferring way than they are looking at
it as a relationship between the sensing
and the acting
all right wow a lot of stuff
let's go through the abduction
markov blanket discussion
the first part is the statement of
context potentially for a philosophical
background but it's important that
they're placing this
along the lines of
autopoiesis and biology so these are
systems that are self perpetuating
in a diffusive multi-scale self-way
perhaps
but they're self-creating we're not just
taking them as existing
in a certain contrived arrangement five
minutes ago we're thinking about systems
that have
maintained a non-equilibrium steady
state with their environments
and if not the enviro if someone denies
the realism or the anything
um of the environment
then that
can be verbalized and even cognized but
it is not enacted by persistent systems
either from the view from the inside
or like if one just
stops breathing or something like that
or the view from the outside because
again systems with persistent
measurements
have to be at least
doing well enough to persist
amidst the regularities of the
environment
so this is kind of like grounding it in
an evolutionary and developmental
framework but connecting it to the
non-equilibrium steady state maintenance
which is grounding this realism
discussion in a relationship with the
environment
not as like in a priori
then there's a definition of markov
blanket
the blanket state conditional
independence between nodes in a base
graph which doesn't mean that influence
doesn't travel or that those states
aren't semantically about each other
but it means that they're conditionally
independent in a statistical way
external states
in sabosku not sure this author but the
endosomic view
would be like
potentially meaning on the inside like
photons on the retina really are light
it really is the case that that's the
real thing
within that facet of biological function
and internal states described from
exosemiotic perspective so perhaps like
the interpretive view so view from the
inside the true influence of of a
feature
and the kind of studying of it view from
the outside where those agree
you have semiosis like with a stop sign
and it means stop
in the situation with different entities
this speaks directly to active inference
given that the regulation of the entropy
of internal states so all these
functions that we're describing as being
like bounded or constrained or minimized
are having to do with
that interface's surprise control on
action outgoing and then bounded
surprise on perception which is
also very force aged by like the
perceptual control theory and various
motor theories which we've talked about
but like the reflex arc
challenging the way that people
modeled decision making
for example
then
um in many treatments they're
agreeing that people take an
instrumentalist usage
or stance
christian blankets are realist not only
in the non-instrumentalists sense
opens up a whole discussion with non and
anti
but also in the sense of being
non-nominalist entities
and then in this last quote
um
it'd be great to hear more from the
authors about what the modal terms of
reference are but the part that stands
out here is the real possibilities
because for these systems
with these features engaging in this way
their
cognition can be considered real
to the extent it has all of these
features and is tied to the environment
over time and so on
hope that
is one view on it because many
paragraphs in the abductive paper and
inactive paper
if you really engage with their
structured arguments there's so much to
like read in between
and
to respect the way that they've laid out
the argument while also
hopefully now all seeing
interesting ways to connect it so
stephen and then anyone else
yeah this is a little bit
sort of feeding back to you daniel so in
case you've got a thought on this but
because
the
you know the there's the there's the the
biological aspect here that you're
bringing up and i agree with that
and
you know in the work on the brain
tristan's been talking about
moving from say a causal correlation to
a functional correlation
and there can be many ways of getting
somewhere when it's functional
so then but of course in this case
there's a certain element of
what's real in terms of what we
scientifically because it's scientific
realism as a scientist what is really
what's been scientifically deducted
so if it's been deductive it is a
perspective that's being taken so within
the perspective that's being taken on
certain
states non-equilibrium steady states
where is
that
regime of attention the scientific
regime of attention
purely an instrument to be considered or
is it
for the things that it's analyzing that
could be real
so there could be sort of a get out
clause
yet there could still be
phenomenon
rather than
perspectives and logic
sitting underneath that which have
many dynamics to get to the same
outcome so what's your thoughts on that
daniel
my thoughts i want to hear what blue and
dean would say on it okay come on
oh yeah steve first
go ahead go ahead blue
now go for it dean i want to hear what
you have to say okay well
so here here's an interesting thing
about both papers and maybe maybe the
authors of the papers will push back
hard on this but great that's what i'm
used to
both papers take a scientific
perspective on this
very much is my typical perspective
which in my books is easily
as an idiom is
when i see it i'll believe it they want
the evidence right they want it they
want that sort of inductive deductive
piece to sort of sit front and center
they want proof
which is great i get that but what i
think is really fascinating about this
is while they are
holding up
that
that epistemic
priority they're also talking a lot
about
i'll they invert that and they say i'll
believe it
when i see it
so there's a lot of faith in this it
hasn't materialized yet but if i
continue to exist
in a social setting
or as an agent
guess what i gotta have faith that all
this time that keeps
rolling out
i'm going to continue
for whatever purposes goals or
directives i'm taking
to
work through
the not seeing it
until i actually
arrive at that moment where something
materializes and i can say oh
now i have the evidence so there's a
both papers have a real
they play they play with themselves they
dance with themselves in the sense that
they are both papers from an explicit
standpoint saying we we are looking at
the scientifically and mathematically
and yet in order for us to be able to
hold on to this
this
this thought or idea of the fpp being
um
you know i'm i'm i'm i'm
i'm whatever called steady state i've
just lost the expression non-equilibrium
thank you non-equilibrium state state i
do have to believe in something in order
for whatever materialization goal or
outcome i'm i'm moving towards if that's
homeostasis or allostasis or i want to
sandwich five minutes from now i have to
believe in that thing or my agency or my
ability to achieve or attain
before i can actually
have the thing
so
from from from that view alone
i find it really interesting that
there's a certain amount of naivete
in both papers there's a kind of a we
have to tip our hat to this rookie view
that every time we
realize something
there has to be a little bit of faith or
a little bit of belief
in what's going on those priors actually
exist and i'm going to use them
because i want to carry out whatever my
priorities are
and it doesn't matter
whether it's the top downiness of
abduction and logic or the top downiness
of an activism
they both tip their hat to the bottom
uppiness
i gotta kind of have a i gotta kind of
have a
confidence that
that even if it's not here now at some
point
it will either continue the way i want
it to or whatever change i want to
impose on it i have that capacity to
wait it out and have that thing happen
so
yeah that's what i would add to what
stephen was saying
okay
yes so
so
i i'll say a couple things um
i was looking at just now the difference
between a
first and like what is the first in
blanket and i came across a paper that
we're going to have to discuss uh it's
called scientific realism about first in
blankets without literalism and it's by
kimberstein and kirk kirchoff
um so someday we're gonna have to have
that it's a pre-print up on
philosophical archive now so so
apparently like having a real
boundary can be like literal like
there's like a literal interpretation or
a realist interpretation and and so just
like i'm still trying to narrow down
like what is this realist interpretation
of a fristen blanket um
and
yeah
so
it in also a very real sense like what
is the real boundary of a living thing
um like
i don't i can't find my real boundary
like where do i stop and something else
begins um there are like hundreds and
like trillions i don't even know more
non-human cells in my body than there
are human cells like so i always have to
come back to this so what would i be
without all of those non-human things
are those non-human things also me like
but then like you know i'm constantly
like
ingesting new ones and excreting old
ones and and so like and they're coming
into my skin and leaving my skin so
where is my
boundary like do i have to have this
boundary in order for active inference
and like the markov blanket
interpretation to apply i i don't know
that that's
um
necessarily true
so
like i can just get off of it i love
this paper and i love like the semiotic
interpretation in like the abductive
sense like but does it even really
matter like like
so the realest interpretation like to
someone who doesn't believe in like a
shared objective reality is never going
to work
or like can you find the boundary like
what is this line between self and other
or like between
like like i can't find the boundary so
like for me it's all a modeling
perspective um that doesn't lessen the
impact of
this abduction as active inference paper
for me at all like like i really thought
it was a great paper and has a lot of
really cool things to say about
cognition and perception so
like why are we hung up on this still i
don't know
okay both of you go for it and then i'll
add some notes
could i just add one more
i mean i think what
i agree with totally with dean on this
this bottom-up
phenomenon you know that's that's going
to be there in the background right
maybe it's always going to be unknowable
apart from some of these simulations
giving us insights but
i think also what blue is saying there
is for me
this whole boundary question
is where there's the problem with the
systems
discussion
in terms of that being kind of
naturalized
and i think that it because you end up
with because systems are defined that
way what's inside what's outside
and for me the big revelation
and i think for a lot of people maybe in
the biological sciences
it's not so unusual to think this way
but to think about agent-based modelling
to think about where's the agent where's
the agency the teleology
and
that
agency doesn't necessarily sit on a
boundary
in the same way that systems tend to
i mean someone can argue that it doesn't
have to and i'm sure it doesn't but it
ends it nearly always ends up there
right in reality in terms of discourse
so um you know we want that discourse to
be clear we're doing this work with
systems engineering to have it where we
want these clear divisions for the
purpose of ontological discourse so we
know what we're talking about and why
however
which is where maybe there's a challenge
this agent
agency teleology morphological
um dynamics are
something else than that and i'll pass
that to daniel and maybe his ants will
come in somewhere i'm not sure
dean first then i'll go for it i'll be
real quick here so in some of the
diagrams i know
daniel you're you're really good at this
some of the diagrams the markov blanket
is literally a an oval with the word
discrepancy
in it
and so all i would do to
to add on to what blue was saying is
that
if you want a hard physical boundary and
you want to discover what that is
um i think you're looking at it again
what
where is this where is does one thing
end and another thing start as a
relativity question what i'm suggesting
is
if you're looking at the bottom up and
the top down as a relationship not as a
which is which is more powerful or holds
more influence over the other you're
looking at that as a relationship then
it's that relationship
holds
as a discrepancy zone
it's not necessarily something that has
a physical
beginning and end it's kind of
it's kind of fluid
and it
and this is not to say we shouldn't look
at the relativity piece at all it is to
say let's have one eye on the relativity
piece and the other eye on the
relationship piece the discrepancy
between it doesn't it doesn't
lend itself to hard
stops
it's discrepancy if that's all that is
that's just
what it is it means
we're not sure
about anything other than they're
different
we don't know
where
where the separation boundary is but
that's kind of where this whole let's
bring these two papers together thing
came from because
if we're actively inferring
we we can bound around that discrepancy
it doesn't always have to be a partition
that's what the
that's what the affordance is here
potentially if we can have
two things
being held simultaneously or
co-currently
all right wow well
a lot there well first with the
discrepancies textbook figure two three
discrepancy
not a blanket or discrepancy as blanket
of blanket etc
and
that can be a continuous or discrete
value but in non-idealized
like non-singular path of least action
settings
aka real settings there's always a
non-zero value
so that's one way to leave the door
always a little open
in a way that
just having two feet on
zero or one
or any rapid switching strategies of
zeros and ones doesn't really capture
that
in the same way
then blue great question like
we asked a little bit about at the
beginning
why what is leading someone to consider
something
uh
like a blanket in a realist or an
instrumentalist light
and pointed to factors like the
persistence of the organism and the
reality of like the action in flow with
its environment so kind of forces
somebody to say well if the environment
is real then the entity and the actions
and the semiosis of their actions are
real if stop signs are real and stopping
at a stop sign is real and they're all
part of a non-equilibrium steady state
what what further
realism does one want to know than that
like there is a territory
and then this is the maps of the
territory so someone going to go all the
way into territory
skepticism
or how will they then reframe their
stance
um
then
on the just a few other random pieces
this was in live stream three
when we read about communication
in active inference
and they are which is a lot of in the
social inaction setting that we're
bringing this abductive
light to the social and active setting
that's really like
expounded upon in the hippolyta and van
s paper that that goes into a lot of the
scientific and philosophical aspects of
social
um so here
they're
borrowing from the framework of tim
bergen's four questions
and providing
multiple
scales of analysis
that are all like the four y's
and these four y's are kind of like a
two by two quadrant
and so then that allows in
biology
parallel research agendas
and integration
because like the fact that brain regions
are connected to each other up here on
the mechanism side
is part of the picture but it's a yes
and with the pattern of
dna divergence times like you could
imagine situations where they're
correlated or not and they could be
causated or not and it could be either
way of causation or a confounding factor
or any other number of things
and then neither of those have a direct
closed door on like what the bird song
sounds like so without even going into
what the bird song is like interpreted
as there still
is space within that
interpretive or semiotic scientific
approach
that
is
hopefully as we can explore
considering
the research and the application
in a different way than it's been
partitioned
in certain specific analyses in the past
dean
well
so here i'll i'll throw something out
there knowing that i have not really
thought about it more than while i was
listening to you talking
so if it's completely wrong
somebody can can correct me really
quickly i think it's really interesting
that
both of these papers
provide what i would consider to be as a
stable or a stabilizing effect on
what
we might describe as
something resembling strategy
for the potential for strategy
what i'm always thinking about is the
strategy is not behavior behaviors
usually given the label tactics
but but strategy does include the
anticipation and the logic that is
applied and i think that's where
we're not in conflict when we say
there's a triadic and there's a
co-construction of the social scene
because i think both of those things
provide the still stability or the
platform then to strategize
and minimize those prediction errors
so
again we can still we can still build
off of strategy and do
and we can still build off of strategy
and eliminate
constant bad consequential decisions
so
again that's the relationship as as
opposed to
which one of these two approaches these
two top down approaches
is the is the thing that holds the most
sway because at any given time
one or the other or both as long as you
don't get trapped
in one
would actually be the most i would think
would be the most option generating not
option selected because they talk in the
induction paper about
the different types
of abduction
but they do heavily emphasize also that
in the end both of those types the
generating and the selecting
are essentially
you you can't you can't have one without
the other
so
that's an interesting thing to
incorporate here as well
or you need to consider i'm not saying
you have to take it up
but if you did what would that look like
i'll just directly respond a few pieces
there then steven than anyone else so
very interesting connection with
multi-scale
prediction error or free energy
minimization uncertainty reduction
surprisal bounding
in multi-scale systems
and then in this social inactive setting
that
hippolyta and van ness brought to the
forefront
that is
our gripper and gripped
in a way that a little
experiment
on a fixed mirror active inference
system or system described by any of the
conventional mechanics
classical physics mechanics statistical
thermodynamics quantum
kind of just going off on a
prelude to
upcoming discussions with dalton
but i think that we'll pull out an
aspect which is that the bayesian
mechanics
broadens that discussion into the
cognitive dynamics
of active particles
and so in that way a ball falling
becomes like a special case of active
particles falling
that could take various paths based upon
their embodied affordances
even if just described as if like the
baseball is not following the parabola
equation but that's how the real
environment and active particle interact
which is to say semiotically which is
why they both
papers mention abduction in the social
context
and then you mentioned like these two
top-down perspectives
and how when we have the divergence
between among like multi three body
problem we have multiple ideas minimum
of two
hopefully more
and then there are strange attractors
there's
there's live stream 32 there's
livestream 26 everything happens in that
space from the top down
because there's always going to be a
plurality from the bottom up
so the one error that
wouldn't
just be the right coarse graining for
sure
is a singular
eye of mordor
laser
and that leads to
basically the unexpected unexpecteds
with the reality of the bottom up
and then when there's divergences and
continuous state spaces and paths in
between top down
then there's a bi-directional
relationship with the top down and the
bottom up or the inside out and the
outside in because you could even move
amongst those without feeling like we
were like violating a system
to sometimes use a left to right for
time and then we could use right to left
for time and so seeing those kinds of
cognitive moves as accessible
in a social setting
and then cut tying that course lastly to
you said that the two-stroke engine of
abduction with generating and selecting
because the laser is not a generator
and that's the now the analogy of
attention
in a talk down system like we've seen
modeled and mental action
several times stephen
yeah thanks daniel um
would you be able to go back to that
four by four that you had there um
with the ultimate yeah and
i think that this is really important
because
there's also this implicit enlightenment
assumption that was always sitting in
the background
where up is good
and
i think it's really interesting there
that and i think you're absolutely right
we talk about it talks about ultimate
which i think is really curious and it
talks about you know we talk about this
interactions so this kind of interaction
this is the ultimate set of interactions
the robin and
that is what the truth is seen as what's
the rational truth
when we go up and we get enlightened so
then we can project down
on what's there and the idea of that
what's coming up is
interactions that's the general way it's
thought and there was this magic box
called emergence to sort of get around
the fact that really we didn't know
but i would i would challenge that
not not to say that's that's not true in
terms of how it's perceived but
there's another way that bottom up can
be explored and that is another way that
truth can be explored there's there's
rational truth
and there's
which i thought ultimate is quite i get
the sense that that is
very much looking out as this
uh it's in built into those words right
this assumption that of enlightenment
but there's also intimate truth
intimate truth
is different to rational truth
and intimate truth is not about
interactions it's about knowing
okay
it's about a deeper kind of knowing
so when i go down it's not
what's coming up in a bottom up
it's what am i going
well my only way to engage it is to go
down into it does that make sense
and that going down into it
is also valuable
it is not more primitive
than enlightenment
and i think that
um
that that goes to sort of a very
foundational assumption which we don't
even notice it's there about science
that everything's trying to be
enlightened but that
is only partially true and i think
biology sort of knows that but maybe
can't speak to it anyway that's that's
my little piece there
to
try to connect that one layer closer to
i think some academic traditions but by
no mean
uh
normed ones but thanks for everybody for
sharing those
it um reminds me of the direction taken
in the
uh one of the biographies i'll paste in
the title here
this is um evelyn fox keller's biography
of barbara mcclintock
and the title is a feeling for the
organism
and uh
that
takes a
history and philosophy of science
informed view like what is the feeling
for the organism
how does one have a feeling for the
chromosomes like this belief that there
were jumping genes
from
certain psychological um observations
and then
how does that really play out when
somebody is in a context
of professionalism and like expectations
around different people who look
different and so on
so that takes a a holistic look and i
think there is that on this every or
many cases
that kind of story to tell
and so
that is one bridge of connection
blue
from like the evolution standpoint and i
think um
like
part of the question that stephen asked
earlier like can we take multiple
trajectories be it like top down bottom
up to arrive at the same
conclusion or the same like end point
um
and this is something like in evolution
there's like convergent evolution where
you know completely different
genetically unrelated species will
arrive at the same trait or or develop a
very similar appearance that makes
people think like you know before we had
dna relationships like we
had species lumped together because of
their similar appearance that were
actually
completely like unrelated like or very
distant on the phylogenetics scale
um so so like it's an adaptation that we
converge on the same feature or we
converge to the same argument or the
same
like place in some kind of space
and this is something that i think about
a lot um
and just going to like the the quantum
perspective
like can we you know
all go from you know point a to point
like traversing a different trajectory
but like if everything is time
reversible then that's not really
possible like we can't converge to the
same point like we have to follow a
specific path
if time reversibility holds true
sorry had to just like throw that in
there
interesting uh
no let's kind of return to some of our
earlier
frameworks but
fun stuff i guess
um
we knew we wanted to cover the mark on
blanket we have
explored
some of the
threads that justify
the
realist or even
further stance
though we still have a lot of questions
from the last 20 minutes or whatever
about like what leads somebody and what
the implications are for being different
stances causes and consequences of
different stances why does that matter
in general studying crystallography why
does that matter for the social setting
like decision making and governance or
organization
that was a justification broadly
for abduction's
capacity
to be compatible with active inference
and form a type of probably valuable
relationship both directions because
active inference gains these cognitive
features
that were described before base graphs
were invented
analogous to kind of blue's suggestion
that there was classifications that were
some were really insightful others were
false clumpings or lumpings or whatever
before there was a way to look at it
differently
that is some of what grounds
a realist interpretation though again
we're still not fully closed on what it
means to be realist or why it matters
but now let's go to the mark off blanket
inaction concept
and similarly break down their
angle on the blanket
and understand maybe what leads them and
what their suggested implications are
for that stance
what kind of a person do they think
they're being by taking this
cognitive social position
which could be asked of both papers and
all uh speech action
and then um
where's the beef
then
what is the
what is the between
there so anyone can go for it
what is um
something to bring in about an action
blankets
and or how
everything is brought together
in hippolyta and vanessa 21.
yes dean yeah go take your time
so one of the things that i really like
about this paper is again it's
the time it takes
and that they heavily emphasize
that
as part of this co-construction
that that
enables people to gain some sense of
what
it means to be in a now
social situation in fact they they talk
about
and i'm not sure where it is in the
paper but they talk about the fact that
people that are that are um
new to a cultural setting
it requires of them
some
time
in order for them to be able to pick up
on the non-linguistic
non-verbal
non-expressed information that's being
passed within that social realm and that
they're not picking up on
so
so what
what enables that and that's
then when they spend a little bit of
time sort of
talking out
why that could only be then considered a
co-construction the more you do
within that condition the more you pick
up you can't simply be
watching you can't
in fact the transition is going from
spectator to
actual doer and so that's that's a heavy
that's a heavy burden
to put on
the statistical
landscape
because you don't sort of sit there and
go okay so what's the probability that
this person who i can't really
understand because i don't even want
length don't even know what they're
saying because they're speaking a
different language
what's the problem like you don't sit
there and kind of
do those kind of calculations or maybe
you do
but you're just not aware of it and
you're not spending a whole lot of time
with your calculator out
trying to figure out what the what the
distribution is
while you are trying to
co-construct
or co-coordinate
your
your active involvement in this new
thing that you're now
trying to
be a part of
so
that's one of the arguments that i
really like about
their paper they basically say in order
for this to work first thing we have to
appreciate is that there is a temporal
commitment
to making anything happen
going forward you could if you don't
have that temporal commitment if you
check out before you've even checked in
nothing changes nothing happens
so
from a markup blanket standpoint that
that essentially goes back to the
discrepancy question is it is it is it a
hard boundary well you can perceive it
that way there's this limitation now
because i don't speak their language
or
you can look at it as now what is this
what is this evolving discrepancy and
how does it change how does it shift how
does it deviate and then re-conform
eventually oscillating down to some sort
of
agreement
that is the instrumental piece
i'm just saying most people aren't
sitting there calculating that out as
it's
as it's happening they're basically just
trying to figure out what does olay mean
blue want to bring in anything on an
action blankets
instrumentalism and then we can um
after that look at what the inactive
writers say
i think it's been said like in the in
the
inactivist and instrumentalist
blanket perspective i don't know that's
always tends to be like the classic way
that i think about it but let's let's
see what the authors say
all right
let's see in the first half how they set
up this question and then
we'll end with a fork in the road that
we can discuss
all right so they start with
similarly defining
blanket we we could look at the word
overlap in the future but it's a scale
free tool don't know if scale free was
said in the other situation
it's introduced as a statistical tool
that allows us to interpret
and then again we see allow for
interpreting
so
the language has already conveyed
certain
flexibilities
if one is to take a charitable
though narrow reading
so this isn't the only way to read but
just in terms of how
below the surface an argument is framed
as in
as in addition to
the direct rhetoric
um
immediately moving to the relationship
with the physical boundary
in the abductive case we saw
highlighting of
the reality of the closure of the action
and influenced loop
but there wasn't a justification of a
physical boundary and so i do think it
is interesting the earlier discussion
with like how does the multi-agent or
like agent-based model perspective
as a scientific tool
help us model
blurry systems as like swarms that are a
certain resolution or density away
then
going straight to
the fristen variant
of the markov blanket
where there are already active and
sensory states rather than introducing
it first in the general case like that
it's about statistical insulating sets
that can then under
perhaps some situations be partitioned
to like an incoming
representing sense and then an outgoing
representing action aspect
and so those are the blanket states
sense and action s and a here and then b
in their figure one is the box around s
and a
and then uh the eta and the mu they're
like kind of like flips of each other i
don't think that's the only reason why
they're those letters and they don't
have to be those letters none of them
actually have to be those letters but
this is the connectedness structure or
sparsity
of what
both the authors are describing
all right then here's the fork
it is possible to understand active
inference in two ways
i think we each had a few ways just
today
um a realist view
that the properties of the model should
be expected to exist as an ontological
property
in dot dot ontological being like
not
in the use of using the active inference
ontology
importantly differently enough
but rather describing
the philosophical ontological or real
basis that's why it's associated with
realism
then the second way is the non-realist
view that the model is simply an
instrumental tool
so
we're at the fork
of these two
directions
what is the move dean
my my sense of the movie is that
so
does that not make up a whole and i'm
not saying that in the
tautological sense i'm saying if we're
actively inferring as opposed to looking
at a topic that's titled active
inference
don't we want to
incorporate the entirety the complexity
or for the sake of
for the sake of being able to
to
understand
an action
is is active inference kind of
it is
my question would be how is active
inference actually being used in each of
these papers
is it is it is it
is it founding
the argument that we don't want to
get completing completion around theory
through other minds or is it sitting on
top of that kind of the icing kind of
the
way it it can make sure that we don't go
too
far off the rails my argument is that
it's both
if we're actively inferring
blue any thoughts
i don't know how is active in french
being used in each paper i just went to
go like look like like what what is the
the drive home message i mean maybe
that's something that we can leave for
the dot too
um
where's the graphical abstract
right for all of these strings uh well
it it is hard to fish stuff out of the
abduction paper due to like the lack of
figures um i had to like go find my own
figures for for the pretty picture
okay let's look one layer deeper at the
um
the three
ways that they suggest that one can be a
non-realist about markov blankets
it'd be a whole other
intersection map with where's
non-realist anti-realist
pro-instrumentalist just
we could do political compasses all over
the map
um and
there would be even second level
questions about how things are defined
in what periods of times and just it's
all good
and so we try to
follow
these again
i i like dean the way that you've
brought it back to like navigating in
this continuous space between two
ferns
between two poles
um
at minimum
and then
that stays in a kind of dynamic
navigational setting
it's and then if you're the moth that's
uh if you can't go too close to the
lantern either lantern
if you hit one then you die
so your flight stops there
so
that i think
puts a very
meaningful uh interpretive layer
because just like
mentioned the figures help with
interpretation
and shorter lists help like there's
three reasons why i'm against this here
they are one two and three those are
important structures
yet also there's a reason that people
don't communicate through outlines
outside of certain situations
okay
so tangent but what are the three ways
that they're suggesting one can be a
non-realist about markov blankets
one
meaning less
semantic tools
this is going to be i think very
interesting
they do not hold semantic value
interpretive
value
linguistic or otherwise
other than that constructed by using
them to understand or predict behavior
in the situation where the scientist is
studying the stop sign
they could say yet the statistical edge
for me at mine
is
being used instrumentally
and there would be a valid stance
but especially when we take this
semiotic
view which is very similar to semantic
and they have similar seed but the
semiosis
with the stop sign and the actual
stopping and the social and action of
stopping and the development of the
agent that led to them having that
belief in that context
that isn't just setting it up in terms
of
merely propositional logic
which we hinted towards
in the dot zero and
many many of the pearson the commons.org
articles lay it out much deeper but
abduction is not
um a static
set of rules alone
the generating selection cycle includes
at the very least
structured novelty arising
from internal external and everything
between
and a continuous type attention
distribution
and strategy on attention and so on so
it's a much richer setting
than potentially
semantic which can mean in certain
settings symbolic which is to say the
kind of symbolic logic carried out by
like a turing machine which can still be
extensive so even a generous
interpretation is still very
um
plausible
but there's something different about
semiosis
and the biosemiotic that was mentioned
in the other paper
that is not one and the same as the
researchers modeling of
and that was also
explored
well by yellow burnberg in the 2016
paper the anticipating brain is not a
scientist
which contrasted a scientific analysis
modality
with
the cognitive system as cognizer and
distinguishing cognitive science in a
way from that through ecological
psychology dean
yeah i was just going to
tag on to that i i think it in order for
this to happen i think in theory it's
easy to say
um
we don't place a waiting on our priors
i simply don't i remain objective
throughout all of this but i don't think
that most of us even when we take that
real really strict scientific
stance are aware of the priorities
and the weights that we have
even subconsciously applied
so
again
i think i think
you can say
um
there's no there's no value add to this
i'm just i'm just i've removed myself
from it and i'm just a passive observer
of it
but i'm not sure how how long we remain
passive before we start applying
weights and values to what it is that
we're
analyzing especially in a situation
especially in situational analyses that
are personal and the consequences fall
back on us and now if you're simply
watching something and there is no
consequence upon you as the observer
maybe that's easier to do but if you get
to a place
where the scientist is part of the
experiment
wow
show me how that
that switch gets turned off and you
don't place a weighting on something
very
powerful and true and in many ways
implicitly and explicitly
the kind of messaging sometimes that i
see in the information environment
is about getting people to update their
priors to believe that they're included
in a larger problem
which is an absolutely valid
communication and perspective
and the how
of the path
and the homeostasis and the multi-level
system
and the the critical path it has to
follow
including reflexivity and narrative and
anticipation
and this bottom-up top-down
aspect
it's that is social inaction
like people can argue that there's
different social structures in different
settings
and it doesn't have to be a top bottom
it doesn't have to be any specific
metaphor or psycho psychoanalytic like
lens
basically
um but the one shortcut
to
collapsing all of that complexity
into
a data point
the the this one trick
is to
approach it like an experiment
because that is what the experiment is
in a way it is about finding a manifold
where it's like this tube has this
strand of dna and this set of things
and then that allows the
paint on the wall and all these other
factors of the true context
to be
isolated from that's kind of like the
partial information encapsulation
or just any other type of system
and then potentially we see like with
quantum
yes
some persistent anomalies
that suggested things were not always as
they seemed
however the real case study is not the
quantum mechanics but it's the bayesian
mechanics
with the psychological study
and the neuroimaging study and the
behavioral study
by
all kinds of uh
people
in all social and action settings
and
[Music]
that really does point towards some of
the deeper implications of
interactionism
formal modeling of social and cognitive
systems
one could
step out of that real life
and enter into another
and and situate themselves from like a
third person perspective
and look back onto
this single path plane
and see that as an experimenter
and that is in many ways associated with
metacognition
however
can that observer
claim realism
versus instrumentalism
what where are people speaking from in
terms of that view
i don't know i'm just bringing up that
sort of like are you
where
are you and that really relates to the
self-concept of blue brought up and like
the kind of situatedness with the self
concept and then realist instrumentalist
but let's move on through these points
second reason why one could be a
non-realist about markup blankets
one could merely view them as valuable
fictions
yes okay that allow abstracting certain
features of a phenomena
but a valuable fiction
one could ask are all of the generated
interpretations
fiction's valuable or not
or so does
saying it's a fiction and saying
everything is a fiction
is that um
in what ways is that instrumental or in
what ways is that realist
making a real claim that that is the
stuff which all things are
though it's not of the stuff that
potentially somebody was taught about
atoms in a certain classroom
so the persistent divergence can lead
some to think that one of those is
scientifically grounded and another is
metaphysically grounded
and or open to preference faith
or other
uh
preferences and concerns entering that
discussion
and then um okay the third one is
you could be a non-realist about markov
blankets
because
just because it's the success of the use
of the markup blanket
justifies the acceptance of the
epistemic value of the model
without necessarily making ontological
claims
in other words
just because the epicycle model is
fitting well
doesn't mean it's really an epicycle
just because the circular orbit model is
fitting well
how well 99
until somebody comes along and goes 99.9
with a totally different model structure
so it's kind of like saying
how
how sure could you be about a realist
interpretation of the structure of the
model
when
as part of one's commitment to the
scientific process they might leave the
door open
to some future model with higher
explanatory predictive power design and
control et cetera dean
yeah that's and i don't know where it is
in the
we we actually had it because i was
looking at the slides from the 47-0 this
morning and there's a there's a part
that's highlighted in the other paper
the talks where pierce says leave the
door open that's what abduction is about
it's simply the door is a jar you don't
have the certainty but you have enough
of you have enough
information
to make
a hypothesis not an explanation to best
or not a
something rather the best explanation
but you can now you now have something
to move off of
to to leverage off of and that's because
the door was left open so again you can
come at it from
you can come at this conclusion that the
third one the success of the markov
blanket through the instrumentalist lens
but there's people on the realist side
that are saying the same thing the more
open
the more likely it is that you'll
actually get to the
the specifics sooner
here's a fun
ant example analogy to kind of bring it
back to uh steven's earlier request um
there's a faster is slower or slower is
faster
one can just imagine both ways but the
empirical finding in ants is that during
certain escape
evacuation situations like leaving a
room where alarm pheromone has been
spread
that when there's like a constriction in
the exits so the morphology of the nest
that they've constructed
when there's a constriction
that situation in car traffic jams and
in people
crowd situations can be very deadly
and that it can be associated with like
a crush
situation or a liquid to solid
like jammed in and then a fracture which
can have all kinds of
issues on the center of where it happens
whereas in the ants they slow down their
individual movements
so it wasn't like some orderly queue
everybody get in line and now we're
gonna wait for number so and so to be
called
this was like
their response in the situation
to the biosemiotics
and the niche construction of escape
right
was a slower is faster response
such that yes their morphology as nest
mates helps them like by having legs
that are white out
it they're physically
insulating so it's not to say that that
is the single
thing for a human to semantically keep
in mind in a physical escape setting
but active inference
lets us pull back to
those different settings
and look at the ants
and their view from the inside the
endosymbiosis like the pheromone
perception the neurobiology of the nest
mate and then there's the exosymbiosis
with the scientist
and then
there are
instruments in play
dean
so you're not thinking through ant minds
that would be ttam instead of ttym
however
there is a sense
that there is there is a hive mind at
work even though you cannot necessarily
share
that
hide mind there is no blending there is
an autonomy
and there is a sense that
if if i am
a believer in the top-down version which
is enabled by an activism
if i'm a believer in that i can also
understand
with without thinking through the mind
of a realist
what that realist
perspective is
so
you're not
we're we're not i would i would say
that what thomas and inez wrote
from the from a logical standpoint makes
a a lot of sense
but that doesn't disqualify
me my my thinking
and this other way of thinking
from coexisting
and and and having i don't think i don't
know if the answer watching daniel or
not maybe they are i mean maybe there's
another narrative that daniel will share
with us about when the
ants became aware of him but i'll just
tell you a quick story i
feed magpies i feed orbits
and what the corvids realized is it's me
because they're very quick to
recognize faces
and what they do is they return the
favor i get
i get little
little um
i get bones from from from
dead things that they've eaten i get the
bones set on the same rock that i place
the
the dog food on because they love this
this fish flavored dog food they
actually return things and contribute
back because they want me to continue
that cycle so i don't know if ants do
that but i do do know that other species
whether they would describe it as
knowing my mind
certainly want to influence my behavior
from a strategy standpoint
awesome a lot of points there
so that's
in contrast with a
framework like pan psychism or like
the absence of psychism so just totally
putting aside many of those questions
you described like a pan-intentional
stance
ism
a pan strategism
that allows for complex holobionts blues
microbiome
as well as the human dog supply chain
crow
setting
allowing for those to
exist and be modeled by like decision
making control theory game theory etc
because of the pragmatism of the game
it is like a doorway
into considering all these situations
as something to play some games to
signal through some games to win at in
this way or to have this outcome
so that's pretty uh interesting
then um
there's thinking through
other species that's very interesting
idea and it'd be cool to design
experiences like through games or art
that could allow for different kinds of
communication
and then
on the point in the abductive paper
about the economy of science which we
can return to that discussion of
pearson's concept
it's like thinking through reviewers
minds
and so just seeing also facets
or thinking through my chest opponent's
mind it's not a total emulation
[Music]
but no but being able to
generate interfaces affordances policies
there's so much
in a partial information situation
that the entity has to generate
and the generation scope means that
there has to be a strong selection
mechanism too and those are the cycles
of
temporal
abductive logic
which breaks us
out of
the inductive deductive
static conceptual
dialectic
and this brings pragmatism action
ecological psychology and so on so it's
really fascinating to see what
is flowing
within that space of
formal models of perception cognition
and action
which are thousands of years old and it
will be important to understand so many
of these different threads
because they're not all quantitative
and uh the abductive paper and the
social and active paper are
demonstrating two of the most important
areas where that's the case dean
yeah just go on real quick on that
so it wouldn't matter if i've decided
that i wanted to do a situational
analysis and base that on the very real
gifting
gifting exercise that's going on or at
least i'm interpreting it as a gifting
exercise that would be one approach that
i could take the other approach i could
take would be a very instrumentalist one
in terms of token exchange
either one of those things
would work putting them together
might might
be
even more additive i'm not sure i don't
think it would be confusing i think it
would just
provide two lenses
on the
same
on the same
process
looking at
uh
hippolyta and vanessa's figure two and
three
so here is
a perspective on social
construction
that they're pulling from
non-inactivist or non-active inference
perspectives
the difference with figure 3 is the
social action in figure 2 under the
active inference framework
is the coupling
and so
there doesn't seem like there be even
one kind of thing
that would be captured by this gray box
in the middle of figure 3.
so
play it safe
take an instrumentalist perspective on
this gray box
it's
one very important
node and interpretation
and then pass that you know through the
tubes
to the abductive reviewer
who looks at it and says yes and the
social actors are engaging in abductive
logic
my background in pierce
suggests that abduction
primacy of the generation selection and
the time dynamics and the flow of action
with the environment
from pierce's work
abduction
can be interpreted in a realist
framework
so this can be held instrumentally with
this
view with this eye
and one can then ask whether the
abduction
that you're modeling it doing abductive
logic
may even be able to hold an instrumental
stance
but is it instrumental for the social
actor for the endo semiosis instead of
from the axosemiosis blue
so you kind of took the words right out
of my mouth there good job um so like is
this gray box this
socio-cultural meanings and model based
reasoning like can those
be subsumed
under
exosemiosis
are you asking if can it be a filter
like is exosemiosis
like
the imputation of sociocultural meanings
and model-based reasoning is that
exosamiosis
from the definitions that i've seen in
the usages i've seen it exo means from
the outside endo means insight in
general in scientific words semiosis is
the meaning construction process
so
exosymbiosis is a view from the outside
for example looking at that stop sign
situation unfolds looking at that ant
pheromone situation unfold
whereas the endosemiosis is the
interpretive semiotic process
by which something comes to have an
internal
meaning
which then could be asked whether it's
in a symbolic or a cognitive or an
attention way and all these different
aspects but
i hope that that's an accurate
distinction
anyways are you actually you are you at
i'm trying to make this
simple for my little brain are you
asking whether or not a person can take
a third person perspective
so i'm just like trying to understand
like endosemiosis is very clear
to me
um
but like this exo semiosis like when
when i like look it up right right like
so
um
endosemiosis is like the signal
transmission into the interior that's
like endosymbiosis like the
um
right like the the interpretation of
signs into the inside but like this
exosymbiosis is like between
organisms like the sign interpretation
and signal transmission between
organisms of the same species or of
different species like for example the
ant pheromone like that's what i read as
exosus so when you look at that figure
three like
is that not exosis
i mean it looks like
model representation and what was the
other thing in there so i'm looking for
the
here's a fun view i think on the exo so
yes i think we're in agreement here
endosomosis is like the signaling within
the organism or the view from the inside
but
that right there is the heart of also
the boundary as a physical versus
boundary as a functional so
there's a whole
complexity with biosemiotics which is
usually i think why people talk about
the bio
semiotics and just recognize the
complexity rather than take a stance too
early on that partitioning but then this
one is the exosomatic perspective
constructing messages to alleged
extraterrestrials
so if we're looking who are the authors
who are the authors of that paper
they're listed here douglas a coach
but yeah let's um
well so so just this like sociocultural
meaning imputation and and like in the
meme paper that um daniel and i just put
out and in
um
with rj and marijua um
this semiotic representation is
culturally
like
relative i mean like there's no a stop
sign isn't going to be a stop sign to
like someone in like the aboriginal
like very like native primitive um
like lifestyle right
so
this exo exosymbiotic is like a
transmission between
organisms of the same species but like
also like the same culture i would say
because like how do you you can't
like
and even i don't know if that's true in
pheromones like if pheromones and
different ant species
mean different things like the same
pheromone can have more than one meaning
is that also true
or the same like kind of molecular
compound i mean i think we probably
don't know enough
i think i think i understand what you're
asking now is there
is there an assumed
sense
that there
some some type of form of entanglement
has to be present
for any of that to make sense
to make sense
implies that something has existed
that didn't maybe exist
in the in the in the distant past it
wouldn't exist in a different context
so that that's why the socio-cultural
meanings like like i think of that as
like exo exosimiosis
you
i mean kind of goes without saying that
there's just different
closenesses along different axes
like people who are speaking the same
language but different
vocabularies or
you know
the situation matters so much body
language then
the more
uh distal or different the cognitive
structure is
relative to what
it becomes harder to quote put yourself
in their shoes
and so on um
and i feel like that's a big
question with the multi-scale system
phenomenas whether they're dissipative
or persistent
diverse intelligences
understanding what the water we swim in
is cognitively and linguistically
because the water we swim in some of it
is going to be the signal
for something else
it could be the influence signal
like the b matrix in actinf influencing
causal relationships in the world
as part of the water you swim in
it also could be like modifications
through stigmargy niche modification
like your physical influences which
might be the water you swim in in the
sense you don't notice them like many
things that come you of and through us
we don't direct awareness of
so they're like the paint on the walls
in that pcr
experiment with amplifying the dna
because it's the parts that whether we
like it or not
they get condensed down to a dot
or a path
and then that becomes our like sense
making from local partial information
as if a lot of the invisible part we
could just disregard and we do
cognitively like we talked about like
the exhaust heat with chris fields and
quantum like you have to burn
information to pay attention
and therefore and you have to pay
attention to deal with a real complex
niche
so there's a lot of
tensions
in that
path
and
uh especially with this dyad and i'm
sure so much other related work but with
this dyad
and i think with the lens that
dean you helped approach it to with
um
it is putting some of those
threads into a different light
and especially for those who
in this semiotic way
had some bayesian surprise some
cognitive state updating
from any number of different things
that's like proof of concept
social inaction
but not in a
corroded or in a performance art
although who could say it's not
performance art but still a way that
brings the realism into the social
through the formal and other doors
uh dean and then blue
i think i think i'd see both of these
papers as pillars i see them as really
stabilizing for different reasons
and i would rather stand on both of my
feet
and have something stable under both of
them and try to stand on one or have
both feet standing on
one cylinder because i find that i find
that
just based on my form more difficult
but as
as we tried to take up this new season
of live streams and bringing two papers
together that felt like a frontier
moment
and i think that one of the things that
i
hope we have conveyed is that
looking at two things at once is by
nature more complicated
not necessarily complex the complexity
exists in each of the papers but to to
look at two things at once is more
complicated and therefore is more
fraught with the error
of the trial and error
relationship i'm not saying that we've
made a bunch of mistakes but i think
the first
the first rule of generation is
you won't get it right
right away
you will have to again have that
temporal
commitment in order to be able to get
wherever the heck you think you're going
and i i didn't really know where this
was going to go other than
i wonder what happens if we
don't narrow our regime of attention
didn't necessarily know we were widening
it but i did know that at some point
we might get the authors coming on and
asking us
why pick these two i don't think it has
to necessarily be these two papers it's
just that
both of these papers
create and create a nice symphony
right
so
it could be any set of papers
it takes a chocolatier
or a wine connoisseur to really make the
pairing special
yet there's other
situations where any pairing can be
potentially fruitful and insightful like
sometimes i think about that in a
community context like you're always
going to share between zero and one
context
and wherever you are in that continuum
the parts where you're sharing is
awesome and the parts where you're
different we can also respect as great
or the overlap between two papers wow
the word use was opposite
or it was like contrary in some other
way
okay
and then with the stance so then i
thought of um
the kind of like
games where people have to stand on a
single pole
in a in a tropical beautiful location
and try not to fall so i thought when
you have both feet like you said on one
position
narrow
then
buffets of wind are assaults on your
non-equilibrium steady state
especially when it's like which one of
these one person is going to be a
professor
just as an example
um so why not
resist
and return to a fixed mode
because that's like sort of the mode
seeking that we heard about in some of
dalton and maxwell's recent work
the fixed mode is the center of gravity
and then another way that you describe
with like kind of having like a non-zero
divergence and the space between is like
in
basketball the triple threat stance
because you could dribble or pass or
shoot
by like going for the basket
and uh yeah that's a different stance
and it's also in a field of affordances
so it's not just that they're in a
different position like the feet here
are not much wider than the feet here
but this is the investigand mood
as pierce would have uh
maybe alluded to it
that in a context
with an action ecological psychology all
of that in a context
with an instrument
and a game
and something outside the game that
supported the game
all those levels
are in the triple threat but the how did
i get here
why am i on the green one
is a limited context
and
um
yes it's still highly skilled nobody's
questioning how
how much energy is being poured into
doing that thing that's that's hard work
and there's a huge reward for doing it
well
and there's many and so i i
totally agree and and didn't even intend
to that people could have trained a lot
for this one this could be someone who
doesn't play basketball
and so that's why it has to be a little
dynamic and situational but
just seeing them as kind of like extreme
modes of paper interpretation in an
extended paper
interpretive metaphor
one could see
different modes of
receiving
semiosis from literature
or discourse
and then
what is the role of participation
and feedback and then that multi-agent
setting that we mentioned
hope that's not too random
um in our last oh yeah blue go for it
uh so one like pairing of papers that i
would have liked to um have done is this
abductive reasoning paper with um
the chris fields quantum paper the one
from the 40.
like because i was just reminded of it
so much as i was reading through the
paper
and just like learning about abductive
reasoning and what does that look like
and and how like we you know in
abductive reasoning you don't have
complete information it's like partially
observable and so like you just make
your best prediction from like a partial
observation and it made me think of like
the overlapping quantum reference frames
where you don't like it like you can't
get full overlap with someone else's
quantum reference frame like like it's
not like even with perfect learning
there's still going to be some noise um
or some overlap between the quantum
reference or some
incongruence between the
um quantum reference frames some area
that's not overlapping so so i don't
know i just i those two things that
that's like one pairing that i would
have liked to
see
that's what's really interesting like
as alluded to earlier the quantum
broke the glass
on the reflexivity question
[Music]
in philosophy of science i hope that's
not too um
overstated to say and it wasn't the only
piece in the building or the weakening
of the glass but the
earlier mentioned persistent anomaly
regarding experimental context
expanded the scope of certain questions
in science
beyond
discourse in certain cultural circles
during the last like 500 years that
stephen alluded to parts of
so quantum is where this
abductive temporal relationality
it's there when you see it now it's not
protoactive particle oh if the electron
were just a pebble
this wouldn't be happening
or
if the electron were a pebble that were
bigger this wouldn't be happening but
would it not be happening or would it
not be happening because we could
measure it better
all of those questions about
points and particles and waves
under bayesian mechanics
as a mechanics for cognitive particles
the reflexivity now can flow in not just
from
electron scale
but i feel like there are multiple
contact services
with reflexivity
at the semiotic
narrative
ecological
the real scales
outside of the experiment
and i think that is what partially
speaks to
the way that we entered this.one
discussion too
so um in our last
five or ten minutes
what would we like to
have or note 4.2 just to the authors if
they listen to this
in the time between or not we're looking
forward to talking to anybody who wants
to whether it's for the dot 2 or any
point in the future there's always a dot
3 affordance so we hope to continue this
discussion with those who have authored
and those who have not yet authored
because there's so much
to build on on on this vector so both of
you though feel free to as long as you
would like
just mention any points that you want to
discuss for next week
dean um had brought up earlier like
where
where is active inference is it is it
the basis is it like resting on top of
is there some kind of duality there i
think like that's something that i would
like to
kind of look back at each paper and and
figure out like where i where i want to
put
active inference in that pillar or on
that pillar
or is it the pillar i don't know
yeah are we going to be able to go with
our active inference colored highlighter
and say okay these two words yep or you
know this clause yep this paragraph
with this paper
or this interaction of the paper
this tool developed by the paper
where would one be looking to highlight
how i saw the paper
dean
because i know stephen would completely
agree with luke can i just get you to
put behind where in brackets when
his act of inference
because again i think that matters so
much if we're talking about abductive
logic
and retroduction the other thing is is
that
i i i
i hope that that blue's
thinking
about
well what
what if we pulled other papers and
entangled them what what fight back i
hope that's an opening
and i will say this
it takes an incredible amount of
preparation
to pull two papers together and not
do the proper respect for the amount of
work that the
authors the originators of that work
have done
so whatever the whatever the preparation
is in terms of quantifying it for a
single paper to do it
justice
it's many multiples of that to quote two
papers but i think
if we are going to be active infers
not just subject matter experts on
active inference
that that exercise as difficult and as
time consuming as it is
it literally it literally changes the
game because we talked about the game
here quite a bit today which again i
didn't think that was going to come up
but thank goodness it did
because it's not oppositional the game
can be
everybody gets in the canoe
and works together to arrive at the
hawaiian islands that can literally
literally be the game
right it doesn't have to be a
competition
it's not a race it's do we survive
given the limited amount of information
that we need to glean here
as as as
important to our our ability to continue
on i think that's what being an active
infer is
that's where the shift from a subject
matter expert to a prediction matter
expert actually transitions
so
i want to thank people again
for what feels like hanging yourself out
there in a real risky way
because it is risky that's what it is
thanks
again there's so much to say i hope that
it's an honor and a privilege to
be in epistemic spaces
and have
one's uh homeostatic variables
secured so that opens up an amazing
space and approach
um the temporal aspect of abduction
sounds so great to return to
because i think another one of those
points of contact communication
is the dynamic what were the only
formalisms in either paper in terms of
like equations and mathematical symbols
it was three representations of
dynamical systems
of hipolito and van ness
to connect and ground
a contact point from where they were
taking a stance and a skilled
performance
into
the mathematical symbolic
scientific someone says this paper is a
philosophy paper yes but it has
equations so
that is gonna come to be something
different
um and then
you thought reading a paper would change
the game
but reading multiple papers changes the
game and it is in a way true it uh is
more
reds to keep in mind
because
at least under some
norms and preferences for paper
discussions
like personally i prefer
and find myself at home when people
don't extensively speak
from what a person thought and take the
endosomic perspective from them
or from like a whole culture which seems
implausible to me
but
situates the exosus of themself
in relationship with a non-trivial
endosymbiosis
and where do those two
threads meet in the blanket
which is
in potentially its most elegant coarse
graining
represented by the gray box here
and why would we want to delimit
or even grip
maybe the grippers that we have at this
point
are like
car pliers
and this is something very different
and or something active
so
at this or any point in time it seems
absolutely valid
to look at the structure of figure two
and three
and hold so many stances
at once or in rapid
navigation so
wow what a fun discussion
thanks steven for joining in blue and
dean
and we will look forward to some
interesting times in the
dot 2 and beyond so
peace out
you